Every single boardroom is talking about stablecoins right now.
Every single public shareholder is talking about stablecoins right now.
I was on with one of the biggest traditional asset managers in the world this morning.
Why did it was on them?
They have reached out to talk about stablecoins, right?
There's no world in which you are a large investor, shareholder, company, etc.
That you're not actively thinking about your stablecoin strategy today.
Everyone, welcome to Unchained, your no-hape resource for all things crypto.
I'm your host, Laura Shin.
Before we continue, we'll take a quick word from the sponsors to make the show possible.
Finance is the world's #1 crypto exchange.
Trusted by over 290 million users.
With industry-leading liquidity, security, and a wide range of digital asset products,
Binance is the place to buy, sell, trade, and earn crypto.
Download Binance today to get started.
Today's topic is stablecoins part two.
We're back with Rob Haddock, general partner at Dragonfly,
who is now joined by Sam McPherson, co-founder and CEO of Phoenix Labs.
Welcome, Rob and Sam.
Good to be here.
Hey, Laura.
So our initial stablecoin discussion was with Rob and Mumtaz of Solana and Helius.
And we got into a lot of things, but the stablecoin space is so competitive right now
that we really only ended up scratching the surface with discussions of things
like Tether and Circle.
And there are so many other players that we just didn't even get to talk about.
And one of the really big ones that we didn't get to discuss is Athena.
So why don't we start there?
Something that is kind of interesting.
So it's the third largest stablecoin, but actually ever since October 10th, its market
cap has dropped significantly from 15 billion to 10 billion.
And obviously, the reasons for that aren't necessarily Athena's fault, which is kind
of interesting.
So, you know, why do you think that is, how do you think they can come back from that?
And then just generally, how would you position them in this kind of great stablecoin race
that we're seeing, you know, take off?
And why don't we start with you, Rob?
Yeah.
So I guess there was really two questions in there, wouldn't it, which, okay, so why
is this the cap come down over time, then also, I mean, since we've had the leverage
washout and then also, you know, how do we see them playing in the future?
I think those are a little bit of different questions.
So one is, okay, well, there's USD and there's USTB, right?
So those are the two different stablecoins that Athena has today.
USD is the one that is more well known.
It's the larger asset.
That's the one that is the asset that was, you know, at question on finance when we had
the leverage washout a few weeks ago.
USD is the one that is essentially collateralized by crypto assets, but and, you know, the yield
comes from, if you stake USD from, you know, the basis trade, which I think a lot of people
understand now and probably at least this audience does.
Then there's USDP and USDP is the, you know, version of the Athena stablecoin that is essentially
treasury backed.
So just sort of like any other, you know, payment stablecoin that a lot of other people
have used across, you know, a bunch of different types of assets.
That is also in the US issued or just moved over actually to be entirely issued through
Anchorage in a compliant manner with Genius Act for whenever that that goes live.
And so I just want to bifurcate those two a little bit.
For USD, obviously having that being the one that most people are focused on, having come
down in market cap is in part because what has also happened is that the yield on basis
has come down, right?
So a lot of people use USD as a product to one, stake it and then get yield.
And so the way it works, obviously with the basis trade, maybe this is obvious, but when
you go call it long, a Bitcoin spot and you go short a Bitcoin future, you're getting
paid for the funding rate.
The funding rate is a function of how bullish or bearish or just how much leverage people
have in the ecosystem when they want to go and trade a specific token.
Well, you know, obviously, I guess two weeks ago today, we had the largest leverage wash
out in crypto history.
So the demand for leverage has come down quite a bit.
We then had more liquidations earlier this week when we saw the, we've traded down the
past few days since the Fed median.
And so that, you know, yield that you get paid on the basis trade has come down quite
a bit.
And so there's just, you know, what's people think about, okay, well, their relative return
on the risk-free rate, we've seen a just less demand for that yield.
And then we've seen some deleveraging and some of the DeFi, you know, native protocol
things that are happening there.
And so that's to be expected.
I think USDA and Athena are somewhat procyclical.
And I think that it will continue to happen because of the fact that as the cycle is doing
well, like, you know, you get more yield and the more people will want to be in that asset.
So that's that piece.
And sorry if this is the long-winded answer, but I think important to flush this out.
Then there's the USTB.
USTB has held up pretty well, USB also backs USDA and is a call out of genius compliant.
Stablecoin for, you know, with treasuries behind it.
That's been fine.
That hasn't moved.
And then he said, okay, well, what do I think about the future of Athena?
Well, I think the reality is is what they're doing is they're future-proofing themselves
because they have this asset, the USDA, that is very crypto-native, that is very procyclical
as I mentioned, but they also now have these other business lines.
They have USTB, which is going to be a payment stablecoin through genius that could compete
with, you know, circle and tether.
And then now they have this white-label product that they are also using that can compete
with the likes of the Okoras and the Paxos and the MZeros of the world for, you know,
issuing the call out white-labeled stablecoins as well.
And so, you know, they're doing a little bit of everything because they want to, they understand
that stablecoins are going to serve a broad variety of use cases.
And yeah, I think, frankly, Guy is maybe the single best founder in DeFi at the moment.
And I just would be shocked to ever bet against him as he tries to grow into all those different
use cases.
So I remain really bullish and where, you know, for full disclosure, one of the biggest backers
of Athena and actually the biggest backer of Athena from the outside.
Yeah, I agree with that about Guy.
Just kind of every single time I talk with him.
It feels like he has a natural instinct for like the exact right answer.
But that's probably just a reflection of how much work he's put in, how much, how prepared
he is for all scenarios.
It's just very apparent every time I talk to him.
Sam, what are you, what are your thoughts about Athena?
Yeah, sure.
So yeah, I agree, Guy has been done an amazing job, props to him and the team.
They've really come out of nowhere and really like shined the cycle for sure.
I've known them for quite a while.
Spark was actually one of the first depositors at size into USC back in, that was beginning
of 2024.
So we were really kind of helping groups drop the protocol back then.
So we did extensive due diligence on it and the whole, the whole construct made sense.
I think what will be helpful is like, so for us as depositors in the protocol, where it
went right and where it went wrong as of more late.
So our history is we've been deploying capital in there to get access to the funding rates
within CFI exchanges.
And so this has sort of just been naturally scaling over like I would say up until about
six months ago for that full year that Athena was growing from about zero to six billion
ish, I would say, they were able to feed all of that into the basis trade.
The problem is that over the years the basis, doing the basis trade became more competitive.
As people, these high yields do not remain, these like opportunities naturally get taken
advantage of by like hedge funds and stuff like that.
So over this year, the competition increased and the capacity for this trade was starting
to hit scaling limits.
And it seems like it was tapping out at about six or so billion ish.
What happened in, I would say, July, so we were depositors into, Spark was depositor
into SUSD primarily and the yield was quite good up until about June.
What happened then is that there was these arrangements between like, say, Athena and
Ave to do like, say, liquid leverage, which was sort of putting a lot of yield into this
sort of like boosted TVL stuff is like, it's a sort of more of a leverage game.
Less of like a direct deployment into the basis.
And so this made SUSD less attractive for Spark as sort of a yield generation strategy.
And then furthermore, with the integration of, say, Binance with the 12% guaranteed yield,
this was finally most of the yield into these deployments, which was disadvantaged depositors
into SUSD, so since then, Spark has exited entirely.
So the thing about this is like, during bull markets, this end with the combined funding
of ENA, this sort of boosted the market up to the market cap that it peaked at about
15 billion.
But I think what's going to happen is it's going to settle out more at where it naturally
sits with like organic capacity within the basis.
And that's more like at this like six or seven billion range, in my opinion.
I mean, I do think it really depends on it.
I mean, so there's one there's organic capacity, so there's okay, well, how much of the basis
do we think?
I think it can be relatively, I think we're something like 35 billion of Bitcoin, OI right
now.
And there's, you know, obviously, ethoI, which is much smaller.
So there's okay, well, how big do we think it can be of that OI and how much basis can
they actually do?
But there's also, I think the point around like, do you think OI continues to increase,
right?
And so like six or seven billion, if we take Sam math to be correct means that okay, well,
we think that, you know, they can be, you know, something like, you know, 10 to whatever,
you know, 15% of the OI in the market, right?
Maybe maybe a little bit bigger, okay, well, should OI increase and because there's more
demand, because it becomes more mainstream, because we get different types of exchanges
and different types of potential venues that people can trade on, and there's just more
people that will come into the space.
And so I think that's the question as well.
It's really a, it's an input of like, how big can they be on a market share perspective,
but then also how big can the market itself be.
And but I think, of course, this is why we're seeing a lot of, you know, interest and doing
things like USTB and, you know, white labels that are backed by by charge rates like USTB,
et cetera.
Yeah.
Well, let's talk about that stable coin to the service part of their business because
obviously now we're seeing there are so many chains that are doing or even apps like Jupiter
has, Jupiter has, Jupiter has, mega ETH has, MUSD, SWE has, SWE, USTE.
So do you, do you feel like we're just going to keep seeing these, you know, like protocol
native chains that are, sorry, stable coins.
And if so, then like, is this, is this going to be a bigger and bigger part of Athena's
business?
Or, yeah, where do you see that trend going?
Yeah, I guess I can take that.
So yeah, this trend of protocols, chains having ownership of like the back end of their stable
coins, I think this trend is only going to accelerate.
I like, definitely, you know, you see with like the hyper liquid situation where they're
not really down with paying, you know, the, the, all the yield to circle in coinbase and
so naturally they want their own stable coin where they can get access to the underlying
treasury yield.
So I definitely think that, that trend is, is here to stay.
This space is, is quite competitive.
There's lots of people vying for this sort of stable coin as a service, you know, you
have Paxos and zero, various others.
So yeah, it's definitely here to stay.
So an interesting point is, so from Sparksview, as we like have access to the most, like one
of the largest amounts of on-chain stable coin reserves, currently over 9 billion in
USDS, we're able to facilitate liquidity bootstrapping between all these different types of stable
coins.
For example, recently there was an announcement that Spark did a deal with PayPal to bootstrap
PiUSD.
So Spark is behind the scenes, sort of deploying its own balance sheet to facilitate liquidity
with PiUSD with more liquid stable coins such as USDC and USDT as well as USDS.
And so this is really helpful for all this, you know, Cambrian explosion of stable coins
that are going to be emerging, Spark is able to provide this sort of liquidity infrastructure
on demand and sort of at a very planned scale to bootstrap these stable coins within DeFi.
So I'm going to I'm going to disagree with Sam a little bit.
There was a lot of tailwind behind this idea of like a white-label stable coin, both DeFi
native and non-DeFi native, right after the hyper liquid situation, you know, especially
with, you know, the amount of attention that the hyper liquid situation brought on and you
know, all the people who put in proposals, clearly that was, I think, the top for interestingly
is in the near term.
So we had, I think right after that from what we've seen, a lot of the protocols, a lot
of the chains, they all reached out and they said, Hey, listen, we want to figure out how
to do something.
We want to have, you know, call it, but we want to make sure that the stable coin is benefiting
our chain and not, you know, necessarily benefit in somebody else.
What we've seen and what we've heard over the last, you know, call it one and a half since
that happened is that a lot of people have realized that it's actually quite hard to
align incentives around everybody within your ecosystem to do that.
And so especially if you're, you know, in the hyper liquid case, you know, it's an application
that is, you know, first and by the way, it's an application first where, you know, that's
99% of what's happening in the hyper liquid ecosystem and then there's, you know, some
of these builders are around the space, we just don't have yet a lot of, a lot of use
cases, a lot of, you know, volume other than potentially, you know, being front ends for,
you know, hyper liquid itself, right?
And so when you already have a thriving ecosystem, it's really hard to get, you know, a protocol
to say, yeah, I want to align with, you know, the chain, but then I also want this other
protocol to align with the chain and get all the protocols around the table.
And so that's why you've seen people like Jupiter and others do their own stable coin.
And what we've seen the least is that people have kind of pulled back a little bit and
instead the idea has been, okay, well, how do we then instead incentivize maybe the people
that we, you know, care more about or that we want to align more with over time.
And so I think, you know, what's also happened is in the USDH case, like it's been, I think
pretty hard, even within the hyper liquid ecosystem to get people around USDH.
So, you know, we've heard of a number of, you know, call it, you know, problems in terms
of people wanting to align with native markets in USDH and wanting to adopt them relative
to just USDC, right, because of the deeper liquidity, because of the better infrastructure.
And so my expectation is that while white label continues to grow, that we probably doesn't
grow at the pace that like people expected, I think we will probably see a little bit
more white label growth continuing on the, you know, call it on the bank side or, you
know, call it the traditional financial player side, because there's like real incentives
around owning those economics.
But when you're when you're an ecosystem and not an application, I think it's a lot tougher
and it's a lot tougher when you're entirely on chain versus versus doing some stuff off
chain because of the ability and the need to like bootstrap a lot of liquidity in these
liquidity pools and et cetera.
And so I think it's probably not going to grow at the pace that like maybe, you know, Merton
I talked about a few weeks ago.
So actually, I completely agree with you liquidity is the whole thing.
And so this is where on chain stablecoin protocols that are, you know, fractional reserve and
able to deploy liquidity as the as the issuer can really step in and shine here.
So some of these new emerging stablecoins, Rob is exactly right, because they're a full
reserve and they have to keep 100% off chain treasury backing as part of being compliant,
pay, they have to pay for market makers to bootstrap liquidity.
These costs are quite expensive, you know, double digit percentages.
But the advantage of on chain stablecoins is that they're able to be these market makers
with these newly emerging stablecoins.
And the rate is much, much cheaper than like normal LPs you have to pay.
So like, yeah, we're talking more like, you know, high single digit percentages versus
like the double digits, percentages of marketing.
Why is this the case?
Is the case because of the demand for stablecoins in general?
So right now we see product market fit and crypto is for stablecoins is just is very clear.
It's just up and to the right, low bear market, it's just going up.
And so right now we have a situation where there is like an excessive amount of demand
for stablecoins.
But on the lending side, there's not the same capacity on the other side.
And so this is how you get the sort of access to cheap capital, you know, potentially even
sometimes cheaper than exists in tradfi because of all this excess demand for stablecoins.
And so this is why protocols like Spark are able to fill this gap for these new stablecoins
and fill in this liquidity bootstrapping issue and do it at a reasonable cost.
Well, so one other thing that's related but maybe a little bit different is the new open
issuance products by bridge in which different applications can have their own stablecoins.
But it's centralized on the back and it's like the company basically creates its own
little mini tether or circle.
So you know, just for Rob where you were talking about, you feel like the Athena's stablecoin
is a service where these white label things might not take off as much as initially thought.
But like, what do you think of something, you know, which is just similar but not quite
the same, you know, this open issuance product?
I mean, open issuance isn't that different than what we're seeing with like Paxos Labs
or what we're seeing with the GORA, you know, even M0 is obviously a different kind of governance
model but like, you know, shared liquidity but, you know, the ability to go and have,
you know, I guess the differences for bridge specifically, you can like plug into like
their like broader ecosystem of what they do or the product capabilities and what they
do horizontally, right, which you don't necessarily have with others.
But I mean, Paxos has on our top rams, they have MTLs, they have their, all the regulated
licenses globally, they have wallet infrastructure, custody infrastructure, et cetera, right?
So it's not really any particularly different.
So it's, I don't know, Athena is, you know, with Anchorage now on the USTB side and the
USTB is what's backing most of these white label products.
It's really kind of the same exact thing.
It doesn't change what Sam is saying in terms of like, and what I mentioned as well in terms
of like needing to bootstrap liquidity, right?
So like if you're going to do something on chain, then you need to have the liquidity
on chain.
You need to pay the people on chain.
And that's true for whether it's, you know, open issuance or Paxos or Bora M0 or anybody
else.
The, or the, the, if you're going to do something that's called like, you know, a payments token
that's within your own call it off chain application that is really only used for your
new use case, then it's a different story.
And then I think it's a different set of potential.
There's a different use case there.
And then there's a probably a different infrastructure that's better for you, right?
And now we're seeing people like Braille get involved there who aren't really involved
on chain, right?
And some others.
And so that's a broader set of use cases that's just like different.
And I think not necessarily comparable to the on chain stuff that Sam's talking about.
Okay.
Um, so let's, we're going to, because there's just so many of these different players to
talk about, we're going to move on to tempo, which is another big one that we didn't get
to last time.
When they launched, there were a lot of jokes made about how the initial structure reminded
people of Libra or DM.
There obviously was this huge kerfuffle about the fact that this was a chain and not an
L2 on Ethereum.
Um, talk a little bit about, you know, what it is that you see as their strategy and,
you know, whether or not you think that this will work for them or whether some of the
critics, you know, were either right or at least had a good point.
Yeah.
So I think in general with all these like launching stablecoins and stablecoin chains,
the key point that is going to make the difference between the successful ones and the not so
successful ones is distribution.
And I think this has been hit on again and again, but it's entirely key.
If you look at all the successful stablecoins, you know, Tether had Bitfinex, so it's a lot
of coin base.
And then, you know, some of these other ones have other exchanges that they're connected
to.
So Tether is really the one that's been able to break out and like become like, used as
like cross exchange settlement emerging markets.
These kind of like more larger use case that's broken out from its like incubating exchange
to our distribution channel in general, but you see a lot more of the like newer emerging
ones.
If they don't have this attachment to some large distribution channel, they're going
to be dead out of the gate basically.
So something like tempo, that's very interesting, like specifically because of the integration
with Stripe.
Stripe is quite big, so like naturally sort of like these are the ones I'm more bullish
on, where there is this distribution connected to it.
And so yeah, I think in general, we still trend of like the FinTechs coming on chain,
the exchange is coming on chain, like base and coin base are like a perfect example
of the way I think everything's going to play out where, you know, all of these FinTechs
and stuff are wanting to go, you know, Robinhood has their own chain.
And so I think they're all going to be progressively coming more and more on chain.
A lot of them will have their own stablecoin.
And like really within their own distribution, it's going to be quite easy to have their
own stablecoin in there.
Breaking out to the next level, that is far more difficult.
And so, you know, I'm not saying one way or the other, we'll just see how the market
goes with that.
Yeah, I think that's the right point, right?
Which is that sort of depends on like how you want to define success here, right?
So when you talk to the tempo team, depending on who you talk to, when you talk to them
and like what they're trying to pitch you, it's either like very stripe aligned or it's
not stripe aligned.
And it's, it's, there's a lot of this like, I think, you know, kind of talking out about
sides in terms of when you talk to the stripe team, like, I know for a fact that they're
actively like pitching a use case like of, oh, hey, we have this consolidated offering
of, you know, tempo plus bridge plus, you know, stripe and we have all these use cases,
like they're going out and actively marketing this and talking to, you know, potential clients
about this.
And in that case, to Sam's point, like, yeah, they have this distribution.
You have this full set of capabilities that, you know, stripe is able to offer across with
bridge and privy and tempo.
And that allows them to bring people on chain, if it makes sense, right?
And so for them, if they want to be on fully on chain, if there's a use case there, if
there's a, you know, maybe it's lower cost, maybe to get through some of the intermediaries,
maybe it's faster, better for cross border, like that makes complete sense, right?
And so they have that distribution piece.
But then you say, okay, a few, a lot of people are trying to tell you when it's more
competitive conversations that this is actually a, you know, a permissionless open source,
you know, chain that we want everybody to build on and it's not actually stripe aligned.
We see all this is the future of payments, right?
And you know, I think maybe by the letter of the law or, you know, if you're, if you're
very just, I guess, if you're really just digging down to like what it actually means
to do those things, maybe that's true, right?
So like, you know, there, maybe there'll be a permissionless validator set.
My guess is that somewhere in between those two things and maybe, and they're doing what
some of the ways they're thinking about, you know, prioritizing or incentivizing stable
coin transactions is more at the technical level versus like, you know, a validator set
or your permissioning, et cetera.
But the question becomes is, is it aligned with stripes economics?
And if that's true, then why would any other PSP ever want to put any sort of volume through
there?
Why would any other network that is theoretically at odds with tempo want to put volume through
it?
They won't, right?
Like PayPal, check out.com.
They will not want to have any of their volume if they come on chain on tempo if it's stripe
aligned, right?
And the same way you hear from the Solana community that they're worried about USDC being the
major stable coin on Solana, because it benefits base and bases, you know, coin is probably
their biggest competitor, right?
And so you're going to see a lot more of that conversation, which is, okay, well, like,
why would I want to benefit my competitor?
And so I think we'll see tempo be successful potentially in this world of which, you know,
hey, listen, we can go in, you know, pitched current stripe clients on a consolidated solution.
I think we'll see, I mean, right now, if you look at payments that are happening on chain,
they're not happening, they're happening mostly on, you know, Ethereum and Tron basically today,
right?
And so if that's true, you know, we have to have some reason for them to shift over the
reason they're happening on Ethereum and Tron Chase, because that's where the liquidity is.
That's where the, the market makers are.
That's where people, you know, actually hold those stable points today.
So they'll have to be some bootstrapping of, you know, of getting that liquidity on.
But then when we have like, call it like real payments flowing through from anyone else,
it really looks like Stripe is trying to be competitive with all of their close partners,
right?
At least over time.
And so it's not clear to me that they'll be able to go broader, right?
And they'll be able to do, you know, pull in those other potential, you know, customers
that, you know, don't necessarily want to benefit Stripe over themselves.
And so I think that's the question that they have to answer and that if there's been a
bit of maybe talking out of, or talking to, you know, kind of both sides of that.
Yeah, just for some examples of those partners, like, once I would put in that category of
being kind of competitive with Stripe, Stripe, when, so Visa, Shopify, Revolute, yeah, Deutsche
Bank, like some of these Mercury, new bank, maybe these, yeah, I mean, it's like a, like
a Shopify rich, like, like, Stripe is actually, they exist today because of Shopify.
Like that partnership between the two of them, Stripe did all the processing for Shopify as
Shopify grew into this big business.
And they were really aligned for a long period of time to continue to be, right?
And so I think the bigger question will be, call it the other, the other PSPs.
But I do think there's also a question about people like Visa, right?
Because Visa has been a long-term aligned, you know, Stripe partner, right, for a long
period of time, but theoretically you can do, you know, with a full suite of applications
we're talking about with Deutsche Stripe, you can now do some sort of transaction outside
of the Visa network, right?
I don't know what, what, you know, somebody like Avisa will do and how they'll react.
You know, they've come out and they've said that they support.
My guess is what actually happens in these cases is, you know, people like Circle or
people like Visa, people like, you know, someday I check out.com, some of the Neo banks to your
point, right?
They'll come out and they'll say, yeah, like we, we support tempo and we want to be close
because, you know, Stripe is a big name and they're powerful and matters.
But they'll push, they'll, they'll, they'll push somebody else, right?
So they'll support it, but they'll incentivize people to go elsewhere.
Like that's what I get.
My, my guess is what will actually happen and, and, you know, some of what we're hearing
in our conversations with people like that.
Yeah, I'm sorry, like when those partners sign up, then, then their competitors will
be pushed to, to use.
I didn't know what you were saying at the end who will be pushed.
Let's give an example of, you know, a, another PSP, right?
So like a checkout.com, right?
Check out.com.
So, so Visa, or, sorry, not Visa, I'm Stripe, they, people use certain part like other payment
service providers support Stripe merchants, right?
And vice versa, right?
So there is call it, you know, people were, if you're going to want to support Stripe,
check out, you're going to want to support a type of Stripe capability, right?
And so a checkout.com might say that we will support tempo because some of my clients might
care, right?
Like that's how the world exists today, right?
But what they're not going to do is they're not ever going to send any volume to tempo
that they're not directed to do, right?
Meaning that they will attend, they will try to push people to other chains that will happen
because they will try not to benefit their competitor if possible, right?
And so that's what we see in traditional payment service processing today, what we see in traditional
networks is that you, everybody needs to support each other because you want to have the capabilities
if you get pushed to do that.
But you're certainly not going to incentivize people or base, or have your base support
be for a competitor's product.
Okay.
I get it.
Yeah.
I mean, it is interesting because I am realizing just it is also intertangled.
So sometimes it's like, you know, you partner with someone just in sort of like a minimal
way because you don't want to hurt yourself, but then you also don't want to necessarily
benefit them.
So all right.
So in a moment, we're going to talk about many of the other ventures in this area, but
first we're going to take a quick word from the sponsors make this show possible.
Finance is the world's number one crypto exchange trusted by over 290 million users globally.
With world-class liquidity, security, and a wide portfolio of digital asset products,
finance makes crypto easy for everyone.
Whether you're new to crypto or a professional, finance offers a simple user experience.
Learn with Finance Academy, browse hundreds of tokens, and track your portfolio on an
easy to use dashboard.
For experienced users, Binance Pro provides industry leading services and bespoke trading
products.
With some of the lowest fees and deepest liquidity in the market, it's no wonder over 290 million
users choose Binance for everything crypto.
Buy, sell, trade, earn, live crypto.
Download Binance today and begin your journey into the future of finance.
Disclaimer, Binance is not available in certain countries, including the US.
Check its terms for more information.
Binance.com/en/terms.
Yet another entry into this space is USAT, which is a brainchild of a tether, and they
now have bowhines at the helm, which is a great get for them.
Obviously, somebody who's extremely well-connected politically, they just announced that they'll
be launching in December with what they say will be 100 million users, such as the user-based
rumble, which is 51 million, they're also investing in two to three other companies,
and we'll focus on the creator economy to launch.
What do you think of their launch strategy?
Yeah, so I think something that's kind of interesting is I think people over index on
like stablecoin issuers.
They actually have a very limited control for creating demand for stablecoins.
So I think a good example of this, so USAT is a great product, but I'm sure they don't
necessarily want all their supply on Tron, for example.
This is what users want, so there's this natural demand in the market about where people want
to use the stablecoin, and oddly enough, the issuers actually have very little control
over this.
It's really like a market demand driven.
Tether's a great company, they've done great work, so I wouldn't bet against them, but
yeah, it remains to be seen how big this stablecoin is going to get.
Yeah, and I think Sam's mostly right, and for the stablecoin issuers themselves, there's
not a ton of ability to drive demand.
I do think that's a little bit different for Tether specifically, because they just keep
acquiring everything that they are trying to use to drive demand.
I mean, this is actually true, I actually think the person most analogous to Tether right
now is not circle, but it's ripple.
If you look at what Ripple is trying to do with RLUSD, right?
So Ripple bought, they bought Hidden Road, called it the second largest prem broker in
this space.
They bought Rail, which is one of the maybe five or six biggest stablecoin orchestrators
in this space.
They bought Jui Treasure, which is like one of the, it's not basically the fifth biggest
like treasury management software that exists, but like to essentially go and stick RLUSD
into those businesses, we're seeing, Tether already has that distribution, that neighbor
in our condition.
You go to Argentina today, like people don't say, "I want a stablecoin," they say, "I want
Tether," right?
Like it has branding that is valuable, whereas in, you know, like Circle does not, USTC does
not, you know, these others don't, but then they also now have Rumble to your point, Laura,
and they have, they're, you know, we've seen them bidding on a bunch of different assets,
investing in a bunch of different things, and they do probably have the ability to call
it push stablecoins, especially as the world gets to call it less crypto-native, and more
of these FinTechs, more of these applications are just like digital dollars, right?
And people like, you know, are just like the benefit of what they, you know, for whatever
reason of having a stablecoin underneath.
If you own that company, you can obviously push the distribution through them.
So I think Tether is going to do a ton of that, they're, you know, they're going to make,
I think it was announced that they're probably going to do like 15 billion of net profit
this year, right?
Like, that's, that's a war chest that they can, and then they're trying to raise a bunch
of money, which has been announced potentially, and so I think they're going to do a ton more
of that, and that will just allow them to continue to try to try distribution.
For USAT specifically in the US, I don't know, that's a different question, right?
So in the US, the US is probably the only place where Tether doesn't have, you know,
call it maybe the US and EU, or the only places where Tether doesn't have like, you know, potentially
that name, brand, recognition, over-circle, right?
And so there's a question around, do we know whether they'll be able to, you know, really
penetrate this market, but listen, the Boheins there, they're politically well-connected.
You know, I'm sure they'll be able to, you know, try some interesting deals and, you know,
buy companies here that they can distribute through as well.
It would be hard for us to bet against them too much, to be honest.
Yeah, yeah, agreed.
I was amused when, I heard you say that Tether and Ripple are maybe the two most similar companies.
It's not how I would normally think about it, but I agree from a war chest perspective.
Yeah, just talk a little bit more about the RLUSD thing, because that's a fascinating thing
to watch, you know, essentially they, I mean, they've been around forever, and they have
a ton of money, but they've never like really had anything that was a successful product.
And then now they're almost cannibalizing XRP by pushing RLUSD.
Do you agree with that, or maybe you don't even agree with that assessment?
I guess as XRP was originally thought of and talked about, like that's true, right?
So if you think about like the history of Ripple, what they were trying to do is like
bank software infrastructure, and then XRP would be like the transfer mechanism that sat
within the middle of it, clearly that never worked, right?
And so like they did some pilots with money grand and some banks and some whoever else.
But like nobody wanted like a 40 wall asset that sat on their balance sheet to be able
to go and transfer, you know, a bunch of value elsewhere.
But I don't know if it's cannibalizing today, because XRP today, I think is primarily just
the war chest, and it's a, you know, call it an exposure to, you know, maybe the Ripple
story and you know, you can debate how much utility it has, maybe it's just a mean coin,
maybe it's...
It's a mean coin.
Yeah, so some form of, you know, Ripple equity somewhere in between.
But RLUSD, I forget what the exact number is today, but it's like 800, 900 million, I
think, of outstanding at the moment, you know, they're growing, you know, they're trying
to push themselves into these things.
It remains, you know, unclear what the ROI will be, of course, but like it's very clear
that RLUSD and Ripple are trying to turn themselves into a stable coin company.
They are buying these places where, you know, volume and liquidity kind of aggregate.
They are buying these things where, you know, they can put a lot of, you know, stable coin
liquidity to work.
I mean, if you look at something like a hidden road, they can probably, you know, easily
put two to three billion dollars to work in stable coin collateral right now, right?
And if that all gets denominated in RLUSD, right, like there's a lot of ROI in that acquisition
for them.
And so I expect that we'll continue to see RLUSD get bigger as they continue to do these
things.
But there's no doubt about it.
They're paying a lot of money to achieve this.
But I guess, you know, why build a $100 billion war chest if you're not going to go use it,
I guess.
Yeah.
So I completely agree with that, like only in crypto can you like get this like the token
comes first and then you can kind of buy your way into long term success.
So I think this is definitely a case of that where the XRP Army is like, definitely one
of the most fanatical groups of people in crypto and they've really boosted up Ripple
to what it is.
And now with all the acquisitions, yeah, these are legit businesses, like Spark interacts
with these we interact with the RLUSD team.
We interact with, you know, on the hidden roadside.
So these are revenue generating businesses and I think, like, I definitely wouldn't bet
against this.
They've got a lot of money and they're actively acquiring key businesses in the space.
All right.
So let's talk about after USAT, let's talk about plasma, which is another big chain that
is piggybacking on the success of USDT, in my opinion, if I'm looking at the structure
of this, basically, it offers zero fee transfers on USDT.
You know, we all saw the plasma ICO was a big success.
The tokenomics of this is it has sort of like an EIP 1559 mechanism, which basically
burns XPL tokens when there's activity in non stable coin uses on the chain.
So, you know, we actually touched on this very briefly in the past episode, actually, but
I was wondering, you know, what you thought about this particular chain, how it might
do and, you know, sort of where you see it in this landscape of competitors.
Yeah, I can start.
So yeah, like, I think with all these chains, it comes back to this thing, which is distribution.
And so, you know, plasma has had a very splashy entrance into the scene, but now it's really
on them to, you know, get the get the user base.
And so, I haven't seen that yet, and like, this is really what they're going to need
to do to convert this into a long-term durable business.
As of right now, most of the TGL is being funded by token emissions.
And so, this, we know this is not sustainable in the long run, but it's a very good boots
dropping program.
So, you know, I'm not super in the weeds of what they're doing, but yeah, it's really
with any of these stablecoin chains, you know, there's like a new one every day.
It's really this connection to distribution that's going to bring a long-term sustainability
for the chain.
Yeah.
I don't have a lot to add.
I mean, I think the, there's a couple of ways to think about, you know, some of these
stablecoin chains, right?
So if you think about like a tempo or like a codex, I think, you know, maybe an arc will
be this way too.
I think it remains to be seen some of their marketing, but these are definitely like
more like call it like B2B focused, right?
So these are places where they're, they want to go and figure out distribution with businesses
themselves with, you know, maybe the exchanges, et cetera, they're focused on providing like
a better rail for like global financial systems.
Plasma has definitely taken a little bit more of a call it, I would say retail approach,
right?
So they've built out a lot of these, you know, they focus a lot on their TVL programs, a
lot on bringing people on chain for, you know, the initial, you know, air drop.
They, and as Sam mentioned, that, you know, kind of funding that through emissions, we've
seen that be, I think, both successful and how splashy it came out and also has caused
a lot of the, you know, call it bad price action over, you know, over the last few weeks,
as people kind of, you know, kind of take profits on, on those.
And they've come out and they've done, you know, call it an incredible job marketing.
They've talked about, you know, wanting to launch plasma one, which is their, you know,
call it like direct to retail kind of neo bank, you know, clearly, if they can go and build
a neo bank, it's of real scale and put, you know, people underneath it on their chain,
like that'll be a huge win for them.
I think, you know, there is a question around whether like the chain or the neo bank is
meant to come first, right?
So, or how much easier it is to do one versus the other, like, it would probably be easier,
I'm guessing, for new bank to launch a chain and put a bunch of people, a revolution to
launch a chain and put a bunch of people on their chain versus like plasma to launch a
neo bank and find distribution outside of crypto natives who aren't just farming the
token.
But, you know, listen, I, they've done an incredible job in terms of marketing today.
And so, you know, I'm interested to see how, you know, how that evolves.
I know they're also doing some of these, like, you know, call it exchange to exchange
transfers.
So, you know, a lot of one of the things that happens on Tron quite a bit on USDT is like,
you know, people moving money between, or the exchanges themselves, money money between
their treasury and, and also between, you know, their exchange and another exchange.
I know plasma has been trying to make a little bit of a headroads and inroads there as well.
Very unclear to me, like, you know, if that's like valuable, right?
But it does allow you to go and say, hey, listen, I got this amount of transaction volume on
my chain, which, you know, might, might need to be good for the token price.
But definitely, you know, call it from a go-to-market perspective, they're, they've, you know, approached
things a little bit differently than, you know, I think some of those others.
Okay.
So, another big player is Ark.
But there's more details that have come out since the last conversation with Rob and
Mert.
So, Circle has now deployed the test net and they included, or they allowed 100 financial
institutions or more than 100 financial institutions, asset managers and tech firms, to, you know,
to start using it.
So, BlackRock, Visa, HSBC, Anthropic were some of the ones named.
There were also, oh, yeah, sorry, some of the others are State Street, Deutsche Bank,
and Basko.
And then they have, like, a bunch of different stablecoin issuers around the globe.
So, you know, one in Australia, one in Brazil, one in Mexico, one in the Philippines.
You know, what do you think, when you, when you look at kind of like how they're approaching
this, there's different types of players that they're inviting, you know, what does this
say to you about their strategy and how effective do you think it'll be?
Yeah.
So, I feel like I'm repeating myself a bit, but yeah, this is a stablecoin issuer, which
is Circle.
They do not have access to the distribution.
This is why we're there partnered with Coinbase.
And so, bootstrapping chain is a very hard thing to do if you don't have your own user
base to bring along.
So, maybe this is more like a B2B thing, I guess.
And in which case, like, you know, what, yeah, the business case is a little bit unclear
to me, but, you know, they could surprise us with some sort of a strategy that I'm not
aware of.
Yeah, actually, just, sorry, I did, so I didn't read the entire question I had written, but
part of what I had also written was to me, it looked like they were, you know, kind of
focusing more on that institutional or B2B market.
And I think what some of the language that I saw was that they're, they're aiming to
be a base layer for financial services from tokenize, for financial services, we'll leave
it there.
Cool.
Yeah, I mean, lots of people are launching these types of chains, so, we'll see, I mean,
at Spark, we're like, we're happy to just see how the market plays out and really activate
support with our stablecoin allocation system, cross-chain stablecoin allocation system for
whoever the winners of the market are.
So, yeah, we're pretty, we're pretty agnostic about this.
But yeah, network effects are extremely hard thing to overcome.
And so, a lot of, like, the RWA activity just continues to compound on Ethereum.
And so, bootstrapping a new stable, new chain in general, like, one, you got to bring distribution
that's to get even in the door.
But then overcoming the sort of natural network effects in any network is going to be a hard
thing to overcome.
So, my base case is that RWA's just continue to compound on Ethereum as that is the market
leader right now.
Yeah, I mean, on the, it's definitely to be focused, like I mentioned, I think in the
last one, I think like them and Tempo and Codex are kind of focused on that space.
You kind of hear them all say the same thing, which is like, okay, well, we're going to
build an FX and we're going to have like opt-in privacy and we're going to have, you know,
sort of, you know, integration into, like, you know, certain types of like end, you know,
bank counts directly, we're going to be able to do better reconciliation, like, you know,
things like this, right?
And so, I, we'll see how differentiated they actually are in a technical perspective.
It sounds like Tempo will probably be the most differentiated from a technical perspective.
Obviously, they have the, the Reth team there and, and paradigm there who's doing, I think,
most of the work specifically and they've, you know, obviously great, great engineers.
And so, I expect the, the arc and to be a little bit more, call it like out of the box
similar to what Codex is, which is on the OP stack.
But you know, we'll see, right?
Now, I guess the question around, okay, well, you know, distribution, well, you know, circle
announced CPN back in May, they launched it pretty soon after, you know, we're now like
several months into it, you know, I happen, you know, I've seen people.
Yeah, sorry, CPN Circle Payments Network, which is sort of like a, a standard and a set
of APIs for people to, you know, kind of send and receive quotes from each other, but is
not, you know, on a blockchain itself, it can settle at any other blockchain, right?
You know, what we've seen to the network effect points at SAMSAD is there hasn't really been
very much volume through CPN, maybe as you'd expect relative to, you know, circle otherwise.
There's, you know, I know, I definitely, or at least I have heard from people who would
know that there is, you know, call it more volume that is going through some of these
other payment chains quite a bit more volume, but some of these other payment chains, a
lot of these other, you know, call it quote unquote orchestration providers who are providing
these types of services.
And so, you know, again, that was a network effect point and it was a point around whether
or not, you know, there was real demand for this and whether or not they were actually
adding enough value that they could have a rate, essentially, right?
And so, like, the CPN was plugging into these orchestration players and I was saying, okay,
well, like pay us, or I mean, right now it's free, but over time, you can see how they
would, you know, they would want to be paid for it.
And like, you have to add some sort of extra value for there to be another middleman or
another intermediary to take a take rate, right?
And we just haven't seen that really work there.
And so, okay, well, let's go move to the chain itself, right?
Maybe those two things together will allow for, you know, additional, essentially like
an additional use case that will allow them to, you know, bring volume to both sides.
I think, you know, what are, there are ways of which it is interesting and better to build
an integrated product with your chain itself.
So, you know, some of these specific, you know, stablecoin, like kind of things that
you can do, like the opt in privacy or prioritizing transactions, you know, paying, you know, sponsoring
gas or paying gas with everyone's all that kind of stuff.
Those are the things that you can do.
But at the end of the day, I think what a lot of these chains are probably just going to
do and how they're going to win is they're going to give away some of the like the software
stack for free and they're just going to subsidize, you know, transactions utilizing their own
tokens, right?
And so, if, if I know a circle hasn't talked about this, I don't know if this is true.
I'm completely speculating, but I think it's probably impossible to win the quote unquote
stablecoin chain meta if you don't launch a token.
Tempo is, I mean, I don't know if they're saying they're going to check on that, but
I'm certain they will.
And I am certain that, you know, the others that are doing this well.
And so, circle, I think, is in a murkier situation around whether or not it makes sense for them
to launch a token.
I mean, we've seen the same conversation at base.
If they launch a token, my guess is that we'll do better.
If they don't, I think they'll struggle.
Yeah.
Well, I think so both them and Tempo say they planted a centralized and so if they're
going to do centralized and they do need a token, so it sounds like eventually there
will be.
Yeah.
Let's sort of book Codex.
So, how an in who's, how an in leave of the founder came on the show and, you know, part
of this was like that L2 debate or really the L2 criticism of Tempo.
So Codex is an L2 on Ethereum.
It's built with optimism and it's going to focus on the B2B sector, as you mentioned,
but you know, it's stablecoin focused.
And so what Hounen was, you know, kind of talking about in the show was how he felt
that it made more sense for Stables to be on Ethereum, to be settling to Ethereum.
And I was wondering, you know, since Dragonfly is an investor in Codex, if you could talk
about like how you think about that, because that was such a big thing that people got
really upset about in crypto.
So yeah, so why is it that you think it would make sense for stablecoins to settle to Ethereum,
you know, versus being on their own chain or maybe you think like both will exist?
I don't know.
Yeah.
I mean, I definitely think both will exist.
I think as you, and actually Mert actually said this, I think two weeks ago when we were
had that conversation as well, that he thinks if you're going to have a stablecoin specific
chain, it actually makes more sense to be an L2 than it does to be your own.
Right.
Yeah.
And he made fun of himself because he used the word L2 and he knew people were going to
go after him.
But anyway, yeah, because he's obviously not pro pro L2s generally, but he has a belief
that which I do as well that if you're going to do a call on a stablecoin or payment specific
chain, it should should be an L2.
You know, a big part of that is obviously that as we see, call it more native or based
rollups directly into the ecosystem, like they're going to be better interoperability
than there is across, you know, L1s and other L1s, right?
And so you're going to be able to tap more broadly into, you know, global liquidity.
You're going to be able to tap more broadly into some of the, you know, financial use
cases that are happening elsewhere.
Like if you want to do, you need things like, you know, DEXs and you need, especially if
you're going to do FX, you need, you know, borrow land, but you also, it's, it's going
to be good for a, you know, payments chain to have, you know, call it structure products
and derivatives that, you know, exist that are people can, you know, swap directly into
other ecosystems that may not exist there, right?
And so I think there's also a question around, okay, well, if you want to do, will certain
types of users, especially on the business side, will they want to control their own
economics?
How they want the economics to work, right?
Will they want to potentially be, have their transactions validated within a, you know,
a validator that could theoretically be a fax sanction?
How do they want to think about block construction?
Like how do you want to think about MEV, right?
These things are primarily easier to manage as a, if you have a single sequencer, right?
And you're going to call it like a little bit more centralized, but also not necessarily
like, you know, completely, I mean, we can debate about the spectrum of centralization,
of course.
But like, I think, and then you share the, call it the global use case of Ethereum, the
liquidity with Ethereum.
And so I think it makes complete sense, and that's, you know, part of the, the reason
that we backed codecs as an L2 relative to call it like one of these payment L1s, I also
just think the team is incredibly good out on, and, and MOMO having built, you know, call
it products, both in crypto and outside of crypto and Silicon Valley for years.
And so, you know, we're super bullish on them and, and what they're trying to do.
And so, yeah, I don't know, maybe, maybe say I'm at some perspective too on that as well.
Yeah, sure.
So let me speak from my perspective in terms of like this, this L2 versus L1s for like
payments and stuff like that.
So I agree completely with the premise that L2s are going to be much more important for
payments because precisely because they sit close to Ethereum.
So Spark is actually a big user of Ethereum as a settlement layer with the, and we do like
a capital allocation across all these different chains.
Now right now, most of it is going with finality on the chain.
So no matter which chain you go to, you know, it's about like 20 minutes to settle.
But with improvements like single slot finality, and then, you know, having the L2 settlement
be directly tied into the finality of Ethereum itself, these types of optimizations drastically
improve capital efficiency when you're rapidly kind of moving funds around all these chains.
So I think it's because of this tight connection with the consensus on Ethereum that will like
make L2s a much better place to do payments.
So for our product in particular, we have a product called Spark Savings where we export
this cross chain yield that's generated across all the chains.
And so in order to do that, we have to manage the liquidity on the back end and where the
reserves are sitting and moving it into the best yield generating opportunities as fast
as we can.
So this is where, you know, maybe 20 minutes doesn't seem like a long time, but these
types of inefficiencies will, you know, if they can be eliminated, like get down to like
a minute, you know, a few seconds, like these are the types of improvements that are just
going to compound so that L2 is kind of run away with the payments use case.
So Sam, I know you referenced a little bit of what you're working on at Spark, but we
didn't go into in depth.
And I was just wondering if you could talk a little bit about like how you are approaching
this heightened competition and how, you know, I don't know how much you're talking this
guy, but I would imagine, you know, some of their strategy and thinking as well.
Yeah.
Maybe I could just run over a little bit about like the structure of Sky and how it sits
now and where Spark sits within the Sky ecosystem.
So Sky was previously maker Dow and since the transition, there's been the rebrand, but
also a restructuring of the Dow governance.
It was realized early on this flat Dow structure does not work for making like at scale decisions
about lots of capital.
And so the idea is that Sky converted into more of a, and I want to preface by saying
these are not banks, but I think it's a useful analogy.
So Sky, you can think of it more like a central bank.
So it issues wholesale credit to multiple sub-dows of which Spark is one of those sub-dows.
And you can think of the sub-dows like commercial banks.
They actually interact with the end customers and this sort of stuff.
So Spark itself, we have a couple of different products that we offer.
So the first one is the second largest lending market on Ethereum, currently over 8 billion
in deposits.
So this is like, I think the old school lending of ETH and Bitcoin, you deposit that as collateral
and you could borrow stablecoins against it.
House Sparkland is differentiated is that we're targeting institutions.
We are very institutionally focused a project.
And so we're not listing every collateral into the sun.
The collateral is not re-hypothecated.
This is meant to be a simple set of five or so assets that we know people like to borrow
at its scale and then borrowing stablecoins against that.
And so this lending market has been growing quite well.
It's doubled actually year over year growth.
And we think this is going to continue as institutions continue to come on chain.
The second project I mentioned before, which is the savings, which is cross-chain, earned
product on your stablecoins so you can deposit USDC or USDT and you can earn the Spark universal
savings rate, which we think is the best risk adjusted yield in DeFi.
So currently generating 4.5% and this is at the scale of like billions of dollars.
So you could think of it sort of like a cash product, but outperforming the Fed funds rate
that you get on like treasury bill products.
And then the last product, which is the allocation system that I mentioned before as well.
This is called the Spark liquidity layer.
So this is the yield generation system that generates the yield for savings depositors.
And so this will deploy capital across opportunities in DeFi and CFI access to the funding rate.
It deploys into now the CME, the Superstate USDC.
We're also one of the largest LPs into the Coinbase Bitcoin borrow product on base, actually
even larger than Coinbase itself, funnily enough.
So yeah, we're really kind of a providing liquidity everywhere.
And that is currently 3 billion deployed feeding into the savings rate.
All right.
So before we wrap, let's talk about some of these tradify players that are also now competing
in this space.
I'm going to wrap up a whole bunch of different little news bits.
And you can talk about any of these players or just generally, you know, how you think
about them.
I know obviously some of these players I'm going to mention, they're all quite different
in their business, but so you can kind of pick and choose.
So JP Morgan is experimenting with this deposit token.
These are blockchain based tokens that are backed by the licensed depository institution.
And they represent that a deposit that can be claimed against the issuer.
So I don't know if I fully understand, but when I was looking at this, I was like, okay,
it feels like this is their way of issuing a stablecoin without abandoning the fractional
reserve business or something.
That's kind of maybe how I was thinking about that.
Then we have Visa.
They're now using four stablecoins on four chains, MasterCard, obviously the $2 billion
acquisition of zero hash the other day, which I will just quote, friend guy, because this
is exactly what I thought when I heard the news, which is who the fuck is zero.
Western Union, you know, is making news about it's stablecoin USDP, sorry, USDPT, which may
apparently go by WUSD.
That's like a trademark application that they have filed.
So I'm sure there's other and then obviously money gram that you know, they've been involved
in stablecoins for a while.
They just launched a new app that uses stablecoins on the back end.
It's USDC and Stellar.
I'm sure there's others on a miss, but just, you know, for all these different news that's
like when you were looking at all of these trad fire players that clearly are realizing
that they're being threatened by the stablecoin competition, like how do you think about the
position they're in and, you know, how you think they should handle this, you know, upcoming
disruption.
Yeah, so maybe I'll talk more generally and I was at a money 2020 earlier this week.
So anybody knows what money 2020 is, is I think the largest fintech conference in the
world.
A lot of it also happens to, you know, exist around, not just fintech itself, but like
payments more broadly, you see the banks there, et cetera.
And, you know, I was on a panel and my panel, there was a panel before mine about identity
and there was like 10 people in the panel and then I went backstage, waited for 20 minutes
on my dump or whatever, and then I came out and we were talking about stablecoins and every
seat was taken, right?
And every conversation I had last week during my 2020 with all of the traditional players
was either about one of the two things was about stablecoins or it was about agentic
commerce.
I was at the Fed, the Federal Reserve, last Tuesday, so a week and a half ago, where for
what they called the payments innovation conference, it was primarily a stablecoin thing, but it
was, you know, they also talked about agentic commerce, et cetera, there.
And Governor Waller specifically gave remarks about calling it like a skinny master account
for stablecoin issuers, potentially in another fintechs to get access to Fed payment rails
without a, without necessarily needing to be a regulated bank.
And so I think the reason I say those things and because like, you know, fifth third was
at that event and others is every single boardroom is talking about stablecoins right now.
Every single public shareholder is talking about stablecoins right now, I was on with
one of the biggest traditional asset managers in the world this morning, why did it was
on them?
They had reached out to talk about stablecoins, right?
There is no world in which you are a large investor, shareholder, company, et cetera,
that you're not actively thinking about your stablecoin strategy today.
We had Bill Gurley talk about it on his podcast, you know, a couple of weeks ago, right?
Like this is happening, right?
And so this is not the end of those types of announcements.
This is just the beginning of them.
Some will have more teeth than others.
Some will be more actually like deep than others.
We've seen starts and stops with money grand before, so we'll see what happens here.
But the Western Union thing seems real and we saw the shares traded up afterwards, right?
What does that mean?
That means that like the public markets like this, right?
And so that's an incentive for these companies to continue to go and innovate around this.
And so this isn't stopping, this is going to continue and, you know, I could not be more
bullish for the state of stablecoin adoption in 2026.
Yeah.
Sad.
So like, definitely this is what winning looks like in my view.
And so now the banks, I think previously they've tried to fight things like, you know, you're
not able to forward interest to users, especially when it comes to like these full reserve stable
coins that are just forwarding the risk-free rate.
I think they should always go to users because this is a no, like the only time you should
be generating additional yield is if there's some trade-off in risk.
And so what the banking system has historically done is take advantage of these low-access
users who basically just park their funds in a checking account, they get paid peanuts
and then the banks are earning the treasury rate on the back of that.
And so fundamentally why this is a big margin for banks.
So this is why they're so afraid of stablecoins because once you get the permissionlessness
and openness and composability of DeFi and on-chain accounting, basically the end user,
you no longer are able to take advantage of the end user like this.
And so this is the success of stablecoins is driving the banks to adapt.
And so now they're forced to compete in this new playing field.
So this is why they're coming on chain.
And so this is just a natural progression of the success of the industry.
I expect this to continue.
And yeah, I think it's like with the change in the US regulatory posturing, I think it's
all systems go for a huge amount of growth in the near future.
OK, last very quick question, Rob.
I think you have your ear to the pulse in DC.
Do you know, like if this, you know, interest loophole that the Democrats are calling the,
you know, what happened in genius, do you think that's going to be closed off or do you think
that that will continue?
I don't think it'll be closed where, but I also don't think we're going to get a market
structure bill.
So, you know, there's that conversation as well, but I expect that we're going to see
what's happening.
Like genius, we technically have until January of 27 to do the actual, a lot of the actual
rulemaking.
Right.
And so it's not the end of, you know, this conversation around yield.
It's not the end of the conversation around some of the nuances with stablecoin issuers.
I also think over time, like we have this, like what is ingenious is mostly defining a
quote unquote payment stablecoin.
I think we're going to start having like carve outs for things that are non payment stable
coins, but other types of stablecoins.
So this is going to get more complicated over time.
And I'm sorry.
What does that mean?
Are you talking about like a, a bit old type thing, or what?
What is that?
Well, so I mean, you talked about the deposit token was a deposit token stablecoin or not
or in the case it's not, but but it also means things like, you know, eventually over time,
you know, could payment stablecoin right now needs to be essentially like a narrow bank,
right?
It needs to be one to go and back by a treasury, right?
But is the world in which, you know, a savings stablecoin exists, right?
And it doesn't necessarily need to be one to go and back by a treasure anymore.
Do we have yield stablecoins?
Like these things are probably come in the way of another probably going to get defined
in some way or another, whether that's through legislation or whether that's the rule making
out the regulators themselves.
So we'll see what happens over time.
But I think where genius was the start of what is going to be continued conversation
around this in DC, not the end.
Yeah.
Yeah, that makes so much sense because the definition is so narrow in that.
And obviously there's like 5 billion different creatively is to create a stablecoin.
So okay, you guys, well, we managed to cover at least a lot more, not everything.
I did leave things on the cutting room floor.
So if you are a stablecoin project and you didn't get mentioned, I'm sorry.
I was just like way too much, but Sam and Rob, it was great chatting with you and catch
you all later.
Thanks Laura.
Thanks for having us.
Welcome to this week's news recap.
Let's begin global stablecoin push gains momentum as major players announce new initiatives.
The stablecoin sector saw a wave of major developments this week, underscoring its growing
integration into traditional finance.
The group announced a partnership with coinbase to pilot stablecoin payment services, allowing
institutional clients to move seamlessly between fiat and crypto.
Cities head of payments, Debapama Shen said clients increasingly demand programmable 24/7
payment systems as the bank forecasts a $4 trillion stablecoin market by 2030.
Meanwhile, coinbase deepened its ties to traditional finance through a second partnership with Apollo
global management to expand stablecoin backed lending and tokenized credit products.
Visa also broadened its stablecoin network to four new blockchains, now supporting eight
tokens across 40 countries with stablecoin linked card spending reaching a $2.5 billion
annual run rate elsewhere, Western Union filed a trademark for WUUSD just days after revealing
its USD PT stablecoin on Solana, signaling plans for global remittance integration.
Circle launched the public test net of its arc blockchain, onboarding more than 100 partners,
including BlackRock, HSBC, and Visa.
And stable, a Bitfinex backed layer one focused on USDT payments, announced phase two of its
prediposit campaign following backlash over alleged insider participation in the first
round.
Sam Bankman freed claims FTX quote was never insolvent, end quote, and new online manifesto.
Convicted FTX founder Sam Bankman freed has resurfaced on social media, publishing a 14-page
document claiming the collapsed exchange quote was never insolvent, end quote, and that customers
could have been repaid in full.
Posted to his ex account late Thursday, the document argues that FTX faced only a temporary
liquidity crunch in 2022, which was worsened by its quote, "external council," end quote,
taking control.
Bankman freed asserted that FTX and its sister firm Alameda Research held up to $25 billion
in assets against $13 billion in liabilities, and that if their investments had been retained,
total holdings could now exceed $100 billion, including stakes in anthropic and Robinhood.
The document further claimed the exchange's native FTT token would be worth $22 billion
today.
The post reiterates arguments Bankman freed made a trial where he was convicted on seven
counts of fraud and conspiracy and sentenced to 25 years in prison.
His renewed effort to recast the FTX collapse comes amid reports that allies are lobbying
for a presidential pardon, though prediction markets currently assign the attempt slim
odds.
Securitize and consensus prepare for public market debuts.
BlackRock-backed tokenization platform securitize announced plans to go public through a merger
with Cantor Equity Partners 2, a special-purpose acquisition company sponsored by Cantor Fitzgerald.
The deal values securitize at $1.25 billion in pre-money equity, with the combined firm
set to trade on NASDAQ under the ticker SECZ as early as January.
CEO Carlos Domingo told CNBC that "Tokenization is what everybody's talking about," adding
that the listing will allow investors to "index themselves to tokenization."
Securitize has partnered with firms, including Apollo, KKR, and BlackRock, having helped
launch the latter's BUIDL fund on Ethereum.
The company has tokenized over $4 billion in assets and will digitize its own equity
once public.
Meanwhile, Ethereum developer Consensus, creator of the MetaMask Wallet, is preparing an initial
public offering led by JP Morgan Chase and Goldman Sachs, according to Axios.
The listing would be one of the most significant for an Ethereum native company.
Founded by Joseph Lubin, Consensus develops software that powers decentralized applications
and operates the Linea Layer 2 network.
A company spokesperson said it is, "constantly exploring opportunities to expand its impact."
In related news, a website claiming to be MetaMask's token portal surfaced online,
driving up betting odds of a mask token launch to 35% on polymarket, though the wallet provider
has not confirmed its authenticity and has repeatedly warned users against phishing
attempts.
Zilla, sells $40 million in Ether to fund stock buyback.
Ethereum-focused Treasury firm, ETHZilla, sold $40 million worth of Ether from its reserves
to finance a share repurchase program the company confirmed Monday.
The move follows pressure from activist investor Demetri Capybara Stocks, Seminekin, who recently
acquired a 2.2% stake and urged leadership to address the firm's steep discount to its
net asset value, NAV.
ETHZilla shares had been trading at roughly half the value of its crypto holdings before
the announcement.
Chairman and CEO, McAndrew Rudisill, said the company plans to "continue selling ETH
to repurchase shares until the discount to NAV is normalized."
So far, ETHZilla has bought back $600,000 shares worth $12 million as part of a $250
million buyback plan approved in August.
The firm still holds about $400 million in Ether and its stock jumped more than 14% following
the news.
Founders Fund, led by Peter Thiel, holds a 7.5% stake in the company.
Polymarket set to relaunch in U.S. with sports focus and token plans.
Prediction Market Platform, Polymarket is preparing to re-enter the U.S. within weeks,
marking a major comeback after being forced offshore and fined $1.4 million by the Commodity
Futures Trading Commission in 2022.
The relaunch, expected by late November, will center on sports betting and begin in an invite-only
phase during the peak football and basketball seasons, according to Bloomberg.
The company recently acquired QCX, a licensed derivatives exchange and clearing house, giving
it the regulatory footing needed to operate in the U.S. once again.
Chief Marketing Officer Matthew Modabar confirmed that Polymarket will introduce a native token,
EOLY, and an accompanying airdrop after the domestic rollout.
"We want the token to have true utility and longevity," Modabar said, emphasizing that
the launch will follow only once the U.S. platform is fully established.
MasterCard eyes, $2 billion acquisition of ZeroHash.
MasterCard is reportedly in advanced talks to acquire Chicago-based crypto infrastructure
firm ZeroHash in a deal valued at up to $2 billion, according to Fortune.
Located in 2017, ZeroHash builds blockchain and stablecoin infrastructure that enables
banks and fintechs to launch crypto trading, payments, and tokenization services.
Its clients include Interactive Brokers, Franklin Templeton, and BlackRock's BUIDL fund.
The acquisition would mark MasterCard's latest expansion into digital assets, following its
2021 purchase of blockchain analytics, firm CypherTrace, and its participation in a stablecoin consortium
with Robin Hood and Kraken.
ZeroHash recently raised $104 million in September at a $1 billion valuation backed
by Apollo, Morgan Stanley, and SoFi.
MegaEath token sale draws $1.39 billion in bids oversubscribed nearly 28 times.
Ethereum layer 2, Project MegaEath, has closed its highly anticipated public sale after
attracting over $1.39 billion in commitments from more than 50,000 participants, according
to the project's official post on X.
The auction, which aimed to raise around $50 million, was oversubscribed by 27.8 times,
highlighting intense demand for the platform's native token, MEGA.
MegaEath said that participants who bid below 0.0999 will automatically receive refunds,
while bids at that price are currently being reviewed for allocation.
Final results are expected by November 5th, with refunds for unallocated users to follow.
The sale offered 5% of MEGA's total 10 billion token supply, with the option of a one-year
lockup for a 10% discount.
Developed by MEGA Labs, MEGAath aims to deliver sub-millisecond transaction speeds and process
up to 100,000 transactions per second, drawing backing from prominent figures, including
Ethereum co-founders Vitalik Buterin and Joe Lubin.
Bot sends hyper-liquid's HYPE token, soaring to $98 before crash.
Hyper-liquid's native token, HYPE, briefly surged from $47 to $98, in under a minute
on the decentralized exchange, Lighter, before crashing back to its prior range on Monday.
Lighter attributed the extreme move to a quote "runaway bot" that aggressively cleared
its order book in a low liquidity market.
The platform later removed the price spike from its chart interface, citing user experience
concerns, while emphasizing that on-chain records remain unchanged.
The decision sparked sharp criticism from traders who accused Lighter of obscuring market data.
"Your effectively lying to your users by doing this," Crypto analyst Duo9 said on
X, arguing the exchange should acknowledge its illiquid order books instead.
traders defended the move as practical, given charting limitations.
Blockworks shuts down news division to focus on data expansion.
Crypto Media outlet Blockworks has announced the closure of its news division as part of
a strategic pivot toward data and software products.
co-founder Jason Janowitz said the company is, quote, "becoming a software and data-first
organization," end quote, citing strong growth in its analytics business over the past two
years.
Founded in 2017, Blockworks built its reputation through podcasts, research, events and news
coverage before launching a data platform now used by investors and blockchain firms.
Janowitz noted that demand for, quote, "data as a primary information source has outpaced
traditional reporting."
Unchained is produced by Laura Shin with help from Matt Pilchard, Juan Oranovich, Margaret
Curia and Pam Majumdar.
The weekly recap was written by Juan Oranovich and edited by Stephen Erlich.
Thanks for listening.